A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 8, Accession 8 FA1190
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 8, Accession 8
1958-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations
FA1190
26.13 Cubic Feet 68 document boxes, 1 oversized document box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist. When requesting audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China. The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach. Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received minimal physical rearrangement. RG 8 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into four series: 2 – Exchanges – General; 11 – Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records; 14 – NCUSCR Presidents' Files; and 15 – Clippings and Reference.
Scope and Contents
RG 8 contains records of the U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program, 1996-2014, including files on program and funding, American teachers, and participating schools in the U. S. and China. Other significant materials include Board of Directors Minutes Books from 1966-2007 and individual Members' files; as well as correspondence files for NCUSCR presidents Douglas Murray and John Holden, 1997-2004. There is also a small series of Clippings files, primarily concerning Chinese relations with the U. S., the U. S. S. R., and other Asian countries, mainly for the 1970s- mid-1980s.
- Exchanges - General, 1993-2014; 2
  Scope and Contents
  The general Exchanges series in RG 8 documents the United States – China Teachers Exchange Program (TEP), from its inception in 1996 to 2014. The American Council of Learned Societies sponsored the Teachers Exchange Program from 1996 – 2002, at which point the National Committee assumed its administration and sponsorship. Materials concern the general program and its funding by the Freeman Foundation; and include files on host schools in China and the U. S., as well as individual files for the American teachers who participated in the exchange. Other materials pertain to conferences for Chinese exchange teachers and for returned American teachers. The series also includes InSites program evaluations from 1996-2006.
  Individual teachers' files often include richly detailed reports on their experiences living, working, and traveling in China.
  Files on the teachers from China and records of various orientation programs (both for American and Chinese teachers) are found in RG 1 of the NCUSCR records (FA772). The program newsletter, The Exchange, is also found in this subset of the records.
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - Freeman Foundation: Planning Correspondence and Budget, 1994-1996 (Box 43, Folder 342)
    The Freeman Foundation funded the U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program, which the American Council of Learned Societies initiated in 1995. The ACLS administered the program until 2002, when it transferred to the National Committee's oversight. Margot Landman was program director.
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - Freeman Foundation: Proposals, 1998-2012 (Box 43, Folder 343)
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - Freeman Foundation: Broudy Grant, 1998 (Box 43, Folder 344)
    Grant covered travel expenses to China for Irving and Gloria Broudy.
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - Freeman Foundation: Program Reports, 1996-2010 (Box 43, Folder 345-350)
  - Chinese Schools - Anqing Middle Schools, 2005-2009 (Box 44, Folder 351)
  - Chinese Schools - Beijing Schools, 1996-2009; Still Images: 3.5 x. 5 color prints (Box 44, Folder 352)
    Includes snapshots of Beijing No. 15 Middle School.
  - Chinese Schools - Changqing Oil Field Middle Schools, 2006 (Box 44, Folder 353)
  - Chinese Schools - Changzhou Schools, 1995-2003; Still Images: 2 3x5 color prints (Box 44, Folder 354)
    Chanzhou Education Commission, No. 1 Middle School, No. 2 Middle School, No. 3 Middle School, and Beijiao Middle School. Includes brochures, cards, correspondence, and snapshot of Margot Landman and teachers at No. 2 Middle School, 1995.
  - Chinese Schools - Changzhou Tianjiabing Experimental Middle School, 2002; undated (Box 44, Folder 355)
    Brochure and postcard pack.
  - Chinese Schools - Chengdu Schools, 1997-2009 (Box 44, Folder 356)
    Chengdu No. 7 Middle School, No. 20 Middle School, Jinjiang Middle School, Chengdu.
  - Chinese Schools - Chongqing Schools, 2006 (Box 44, Folder 357)
  - Chinese Schools - Dalian Schools, 1997-2005 (Box 44, Folder 358)
  - Chinese Schools - Hefei Schools, 2003-2009 (Box 44, Folder 359)
    File includes packet of postcards of Hefei No. 1 Senior High School.
  - Chinese Schools - Luoyang Schools, 1998-2006 (Box 44, Folder 360)
  - Chinese Schools - Inner Mongolia Teachers University Affiliated Middle School (Hohhot), 1996-1999 (Box 44, Folder 361)
  - Chinese Schools - Nanjing Schools, 2000-2009 (Box 44, Folder 362)
    Includes brochures.
  - Chinese Schools - Suzhou Schools (General), 2000-2009; Still Images: 6 3x5 color prints (Box 44, Folder 363)
    Includes Suzhou No. 10 Middle School, Suzhou No. 6 Middle School, Suzhou Experimental Primary School, among others. File includes postcards, snapshots of an apartment interior, brochures.
  - Chinese Schools - Suzhou Middle School, 1994-2005; Still Images: 3 3x5 color prints (Box 44, Folder 364)
    Suzhou Middle School of Jiangsu Province, Includes brochures and snapshot photos.
  - Chinese Schools - Suzhou No. 1 Middle School, 1998-2009; Still Images (Box 45, Folder 365)
    Includes brochures, cards, newsletters, school publications, and color snapshots of teachers with Margot Landman, students.
  - Chinese Schools - Suzhou No. 3 Middle School, 1996-2000; Still Image: 5x7 color print, mounted in portfolio frame. (Box 45, Folder 366)
    Includes photo of Margot Landman with teachers.
  - Chinese Schools - Tongling Schools, 2003-2004 (Box 45, Folder 367)
  - Chinese Schools - Xi'an Schools, 2005-2009 (Box 45, Folder 368)
  - Chinese Schools - Yan'an Middle School (Shaanxi), 2005 (Box 45, Folder 369)
  - Chinese Schools - Yangzhou Schools, 1997-2006 (Box 45, Folder 370)
    Xinhua Middle School, Yangzhou Middle School, Yangzhou Teachers College Affiliated Middle School. Includes postcards and brochures.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 1997 January 17-20; Still Image: 1 color 4x6 print (Box 45, Folder 371)
    Includes notes and snapshot of group at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 1998 January 16-19 (Box 45, Folder 372)
    File includes notes on visits and meetings from September 1978 through the January conference.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 1999 January 15-18; Still Images: 26 color 4x6 prints (Box 45, Folder 373)
    Includes snapshots from the conference.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2000 January 14-17; Still Images: 3 prints (Box 45, Folder 374)
    Includes group snapshots with identifications.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2001 - 2003 (Box 45, Folder 375-377)
    Conferences held in mid-January.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2004 January 16-19; Still Images: 4 color 4x6 prints (Box 45, Folder 378)
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2005 January 14-17; Still Images: 2 color 4x6 prints (Box 45, Folder 379)
    Includes snapshots of teachers
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2006 January 13-16; Still Images: 15 color 4x6 prints (Box 45, Folder 380)
    Includes snapshots from the conference, including group photos, with identifications.
  - Chinese Teachers - Mid-Year Conference (New York City), 2007 -2014 (Box 46, Folder 381-386)
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 1998 October 16-18 (Box 46, Folder 387)
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2000 April 7-9; Still Image: 1 color 4x6 print (Box 46, Folder 388)
    Includes snapshot, with identifications.
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2001 April 27-29 (Box 46, Folder 389)
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2002 April 26-28; Still Image: 7 color 4x6 prints (Box 46, Folder 390)
    Includes snapshots of conference, with identifications.
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2003 April 25-27 (Box 46, Folder 391)
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2006 April 28-30 (Box 46, Folder 392)
  - Returned American Teachers Conference (New York City), 2008 March 28-30 (Box 46, Folder 393)
  - Chinese Teachers - Workshop (New York City), 2001 December 15; Still Image: 7 4x6 color prints (Box 46, Folder 394)
    Includes snapshots of visit to Bear Mountain park, October 2001.
  - Chinese Teachers - Orientation, 2003 August (Box 46, Folder 395)
    Four Springs Retreat Center, Middletown, CA. File mainly contains orientation materials.
  - Freeman Foundation: Correspondence, 1995-2011 (Box 47, Folder 396-398)
  - InSites: Correspondence, 1995-2006 (Box 47, Folder 399-401)
  - InSites: Reports, 1996-1998 (Box 47, Folder 402-403)
    Evaluative reports on the ACLS United States - China secondary school teacher exchange program. InSites is a nonprofit research, evaluation, and planning organization.
  - InSites: Reports, 1999-2006 (Box 48, Folder 404-408)
    Evaluative reports on the United States - China Teachers Exchange Program. The National Committee assumed direction of the program in 2002. InSites is a nonprofit research, evaluation, and planning organization.
  - InSites: Reports, 2006 September (Box 48, Folder 409)
    Making the Most of K-12 Educator Study Tour Programs to Asia: A Working Document on Phase 1 of an Evaluative Inquiry. Study commissioned by the Freeman Foundation. File also includes summaries of survey responses from the 1996-1997 and 2000-2001 Teachers Exchange Programs.
  - China Institute, 1995-2000 (Box 48, Folder 410)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with China, 1995-1997; Still Image: 1 4x6 color print. (Box 48, Folder 411)
    Includes snapshot of Margot Landman with Keith Clemenger, 1997.
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with China, 1998-1999; Still Image: 1 4x6 color print. (Box 49, Folder 412)
  - Oxford Associates, Inc., 2001-2005 (Box 49, Folder 413)
  - Primary Source (Boston), 1995-1999 (Box 49, Folder 414)
  - Secondary School Chinese Language Center - Princeton-in-Beijing Program, 1995-2004 (Box 49, Folder 415-416)
    Teacher-training workshop in Beijing for Chinese teachers coming to the U. S.
  - Chinese Service Center for Scholarly Exchange, 1996-1999 (Box 49, Folder 417)
  - Paul Englesberg, 1995-1996 (Box 49, Folder 418)
    Englesberg, professor of education at Western Washington University, was studying teachers' cross-cultural exchange experiences.
  - Mountbatten Internship Programme, 1995-1996 (Box 49, Folder 419)
    Correspondence with Ellen Lautz.
  - New York Council for the Humanities, 1996 (Box 49, Folder 420)
  - Randy Sachter, 1996 (Box 49, Folder 421)
  - Yale - China Association, 1995 (Box 49, Folder 422)
  - PRC Government - Changzhou Municipal Education Commission, 1997-2002 (Box 49, Folder 423)
  - PRC Government - Chengdu Education Commission, 1997 (Box 49, Folder 424)
  - PRC Government - Dalian Municipal Education Commission, 1997-2006 (Box 49, Folder 425)
  - PRC Government - Heilongjiang Education Exchange Center, 2006 (Box 49, Folder 426)
  - PRC Government - Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region Education Department, 1997-1998; Still Image: 1 3x5 color print. PRC Government - Folders Group together (Box 49, Folder 427)
    Includes snapshot of Su Li Ya.
  - PRC Government - Jiangsu Education Commission, 1997; 2006 (Box 49, Folder 428)
  - PRC Government - Shaanxi Education Bureau, 2006 (Box 49, Folder 429)
  - PRC Government - Sichuan Education Commission, 1997 (Box 49, Folder 430)
  - PRC Government - Suzhou Education Commission, 1997-2005 (Box 49, Folder 431)
  - PRC Government - Yangzhou Education Commission, 1997 (Box 49, Folder 432)
  - PRC Government - State Education Commission, 1993-1995; 2003 (Box 49, Folder 433)
  - PRC Government - Consulate General in New York, 1995; 1999; 2002 (Box 49, Folder 434)
  - Chinese Education Association for International Exchange (CEAIE) - Administrators' Delegation, 1998 June 6-25 (Box 49, Folder 435)
  - Chinese Education Association for International Exchange (CEAIE) - Administrators' Delegation, 1999 May - June (Box 49, Folder 436)
  - Chinese Education Association for International Exchange (CEAIE) - Administrators' Delegation, 2002 September - October (Box 50, Folder 437)
  - Chinese Education Association for International Exchange (CEAIE) - Delegation, 2007 October (Box 50, Folder 438)
    Visit to New York University, October 26.
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - General, 1996 (Box 50, Folder 439)
    Michael Holzman report to the ACLS, January 10, 1996, on November 1995 visit to China and meetings with the Chinese Education Association for International Exchange (CEAIE).
  - U. S. - China Teachers Exchange Program - Personnel, 1998-2001 (Box 50, Folder 440)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - personnel material.
    Joshua Goldberg, 1998; Michele Steer, 2001.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 1996 - 1997 (Box 50, Folder 441)
    Summer orientation program at Tarrytown House. Planning and various program materials.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 1998 - 1999; Still Image: 8 4x6 color prints (1998) and 8 3x5 color prints (1999)/ (Box 50, Folder 442)
    Summer orientation program at the Forrestal Hotel, Princeton. Various planning and program materials, notes, and correspondence. Snapshots of tai chi and orientation classes.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2000 July 7-13; Still Images: 2 4x6 color prints (Box 50, Folder 443)
    Forrestal Hotel, Princeton. Various planning and program materials, notes, and correspondence. Snapshots of classes, with identifications.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2001 July 6-12; Still Images: 31 4x6 color prints (Box 50, Folder 444)
    Arden House, Harriman, NY. File includes notes and program materials. Snapshots of programs and participants, with identifications.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2003 July 9-15 (Box 50, Folder 445)
    Arden House, Harriman, NY. File includes notes and program materials.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2004 July 8-14 (Box 50, Folder 446)
    Arden House, Harriman, NY. File includes pad of notes and program materials. Notepad also includes notes, July - December 2004, relating to meetings with Chinese teachers and others.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2006 - 2007; Still Image; 1 4x6 color print (Box 50, Folder 447)
    Thayer Hotel, West Point, NY, July 5-11, 2006 and 2007. Includes one snapshot of Margot Landman and Nick McBurney.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2009 - 2011; Still Images: 8 4x6 color prints (Box 50, Folder 448)
    July pre-departure orientation, held at Thayer Hotel, West Point, NY. Includes snapshots of participants in 2011 program, with identifications.
  - American Teachers Orientation, 2012 - 2013; Still Images: 5 4x6 color prints (Box 50, Folder 449)
    July pre-departure orientation, held at Thayer Hotel, West Point, NY. Includes notes of 2012 programs; snapshots of Margot Landman and participants at 20123 closing dinner.
  - American Teachers - Amper, Susan and Thomas Amper (1998 - 1999), 1997 - 2006; Still Images: 3x5 and 5x7 color prints (Box 50, Folder 450)
    Includes accounts of experiences and snapshots of students and activities in China (including Children's English Speech Contest).
  - American Teachers - Angell, Christopher (2011-2012, Hefei No. 2 Middle School) (Box 50, Folder 451)
  - American Teachers - Ba, Papa Assane (1999-2000, 2003-2004), 1998-2006 (Box 51, Folder 452)
  - American Teachers - Baboomian, Susan (1996-1997, 1998-1999), 1996-2004; Still Images: ca. 49 mainly 3x5 color prints (1 4x6 print) (Box 51, Folder 453-454)
    Includes extensive correspondence and several snapshots of instructional activities, costumes, trips, etc.
  - American Teachers - Bachman, Susan (2003-2004), 2003-2005 (Box 51, Folder 455)
    The 2003-2004 cohort did not travel to China until 2004-2005, because of the 2003 SARS outbreak.
  - American Teachers - Badgley, Perry Bradford (Brad) (2001-2002, 2003-2004), 2001-2009; Still Images: 3 4x6 color prints (Box 51, Folder 456)
    Includes snapshots of teachers and students.
  - American Teachers - Barry, Patricia (1998-1999), 1998-2006; Still Images: ca. 5 4x6 color prints (Box 51, Folder 457-458)
    File includes a few snapshots from her China stay.
  - American Teachers - Becker, Daniel (2003-2004), 2003-2009 (Box 51, Folder 459)
  - American Teachers - Bergeson, Roy and Margaret Bergeson (2000-2001), 2000-2003; Still Images: 1 3x5 color print; 2 oversized color prints (7.75 x 12, 9 x 12). (Box 51, Folder 460)
    Includes snapshot with friends and two images of meeting.
  - American Teachers - Bergeson, Roy and Margaret Bergeson (2000-2001), 2002-2006; Still Images: 4 4x6 color prints (Box 52, Folder 461)
    Includes images from a banquet.
  - American Teachers - Bergeson, Roy and Margaret Bergeson (2000-2001), 2004; DVD
    Foundation Programs Inc. DVD, Glimpses of China: Students' Reflections.Sent by Roy Bergeson to Margot Landman, February 2004.
    Access copy currently unavailable. Researchers interested in accessing digital media in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Please contact an archivist for information.
  - American Teachers - Bianco, Janis (1997-1998), 1997-2004 (Box 52, Folder 462)
  - American Teachers - Bronski, William (1996-1997, 2001-2002, 2003-2004), 1996-2010; 2013; Still Images: 13 3x5 color prints (Box 52, Folder 463-464)
    Includes snapshots of Christmas party and bulletin boards.
  - American Teachers - Broudy, Gloria Berenson and Irving Broudy (1996-1997), 1996-2005; Still Images: 5 color prints (3x5 - 4x6) (Box 52, Folder 465-466)
    The Broudys went to Changzhou in 1996 with a particular interest in improving English language teaching there. In 1998 the Freeman Foundation sponsored their travel to Changzou to conduct a workshop for Chinese teachers of English and to promote exchange partnerships (includes photos of workshop).
  - American Teachers - Bruss, Greg (1997-1998), 1996-2006 (Box 52, Folder 467)
  - American Teachers - Burbank, Davis (2009-2010), 2008-2011 (Box 53, Folder 468)
  - American Teachers - Burnett, Joe Rex (2010-2011) (Box 53, Folder 469)
  - American Teachers - Burress, Joan (1996-1997, 1997-1998, 1998-1999), 1996-2005; Still Images:: 6 color prints (3x5 - 4x6) (Box 53, Folder 470-471)
    Includes student writings and classwork, snapshots of students, holiday celebrations, play.
  - American Teachers - Bush, Theresa (2011-2012) (Box 53, Folder 472)
  - American Teachers - Castle, Margaret (Peggy) (2000-2001), 2000-2004 (Box 53, Folder 473)
  - American Teachers - Cesario, Patricia (2006-2007) (Box 53, Folder 474)
  - American Teachers - Chou, Gail (2004-2005), 2004-2006 (Box 53, Folder 475)
  - American Teachers - Clay, Willy (1997-1998), 1997-2004; Still Images: about 27 color images (3x5 and 1 4x6) (Box 53, Folder 476-477)
    Includes snapshots of China and particularly of daughter at nursery school and with students.
  - American Teachers - Clay, Willy (1997-1998), 1997-2004; CD
    Contents unidentified.
  - American Teachers - Clower, Virginia (2004-2005) (Box 53, Folder 478)
  - American Teachers - Cohen, Peter, and A. M. Rashmini Ernest-Cohen (1996-1997, 2003-2004), 1996-2008 (Box 53, Folder 479-480)
  - American Teachers - Colletti, Frank (2000-2001), 2000-2005 (Box 53, Folder 481)
  - American Teachers - Courtice Hart, Heather (2013-2014) (Box 53, Folder 482)
  - American Teachers - Crispe, Robyn (2010-2011) (Box 54, Folder 483)
  - American Teachers - Crotchett, Kevin (2001-2002), Still Images: 3 3x5 color prints (Box 54, Folder 484)
    Includes snapshots of family and children playing.
  - American Teachers - Dabney, Hayes G., II (1999-2000) (Box 54, Folder 485-486)
  - American Teachers - Davidson, Robert, and Janet Davidson (2007-2008), 2007-2009 (Box 54, Folder 487)
  - American Teachers - De Yoe, Carmen (2001-2002), 2001-2004; Still Images: ca. 42 color prints (4x6-5x7). (Box 54, Folder 488)
    Snapshots with colleagues and students, teaching square dancing; school activities and exhibits about China after her return. Photos include identifications.
  - American Teachers - Dixon, Nyree (2000-2001), 2000-2004; Still Images: 4 4x6 color prints (Box 54, Folder 489)
    Includes pen pal letters and photos of fan dance by her U. S. students; one image of classroom skit in China.
  - American Teachers - Dyro, Stephen (1996-1997), 1996-2004; Still Images: 2 4x6 color prints (Box 54, Folder 490)
    Image of Dyro with U. S. students and playing an instrument.